Finding Aid for John C. Manning papers, 1907-1973
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
John C. Manning papers 1907-1973
Manning, John C. (John Charles), 1893-1967.
4 linear feet
85313 Aa 2
Editor of the Detroit Times, later columnist for the Detroit Free Press. Correspondence, speeches, topical files, photographs, and writings relating to his newspaper career, his interest in Detroit, Michigan, and his involvement with various Catholic organizations and affairs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Manning’s daughter, Mrs. Suzanne Manning Walker (donor no. 6918 ) and came to the library, April 1983.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
John Charles Manning (Jack) was born November 4, 1892 of Irish- American parents in Detroit. After graduating from the University of Detroit, Manning worked as a reporter for the Detroit Free Press. Advised that working for a smaller paper would allow him to try his hand at different aspects of journalism, Manning left Detroit to work for the Duluth News Tribune, the Minneapolis Tribune, and the Chicago Tribune. He returned to Detroit in the early 1920ts and became a sportswriter for the Detroit News. When the Hearst paper, the Detroit Times, opened in 1923, Manning was hired as a reporter and then as city editor. In 1932 he rose to managing editor and became the editor-in-chief by 1938. He remained with the Detroit Times until November 1960 when the paper closed. At that time Manning vent back to the newspaper that had given him his first job, the Detroit Free Press. There he had his own column until his death in 1967.
In his work as a newspaperman and especially in his later years as a columnist, Manning was keenly interested in everything having to do with Detroit. He was particularly aware of the need to preserve Detroit's history. In addition, he was involved in various Catholic layman and ecumenical activities, including an active membership in the Detroit Round Table of Catholics, Jews and Protestants.
The papers of John C. Manning (3.5 linear feet; 1907-1973; bulk 1955-1964)consist of correspondence, speeches, topical files, photographs, and writings relating to his newspaper career, his interest in Detroit, Michigan, and his involvement with various Catholic organizations and affairs. The papers are arranged in five main series: Personal, Correspondence, Speeches, Topical Files, Writings and Photographs.
Subjects:
Catholic Church--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit Free Press.; Detroit (Mich.)--History.; Detroit times.; Journalists--Michigan--Detroit.; American newspapers--Michigan--Detroit.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Detroit (Mich.); Henry Ford Museum and Greenfield Village.; Newspaper industry--Michigan--Detroit.; Mooney, Edward, Archbishop, 1882-1958
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Personal
  The Personal series includes biographical material, awards, invitations, newspaper clippings about Manning himself, publishing contracts with William Randolph Hearst, Jr., and miscellanea.
  - Biographical Material (Box 1)
  - Awards Invitations (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1947-1973 (Box 1)
  - Publishing Contracts 1942-1957 (Box 1)
  - Miscellanea 1907 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series is the largest in the collection. It spans the years 1919-1967, but the greatest concentration of letters is between the years 1960 and 1963. The majority of the letters during these years are routine responses to correspondence from readers of his column. For this reason, correspondence from earlier years tends to be more interesting and diverse. His correspondence includes many letters from important people of his day, especially within the state of Michigan. While many of these letters are simply acknowledgements of Manning's newspaper articles, Manning did have a fairly substantial exchange of letters with Frank Murphy, James Couzens, and his aunt Margaret Manning Couzens (the wife of James Couzens) during the 1930's. He was also on good terms with William Randolph Hearst (Senior and Junior) and Henry Ford II.
  - Undated 1919-May 31, 1961, 21 folders (Box 1)
  - June 1961-May 1963, 22 folders (Box 2)
  - June 1963-1967, 12 folders (Box 3)
- Speeches
  The Speeches series is quite small, consisting of two folders of mostly undated talks. It is not always clear to whom the speeches were given, but many of them seem to have been advice to graduating classes or to students seeking careers in journalism.
  - Talks to various groups undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
- Topical File
  The Topical File contains material on topics of specific interest to Manning. Within this series, there is material concerning the confirmation of Edward Mooney as a Cardinal in February 1946. Manning was assigned to Rome to cover the story, which he considered one of the greatest of his career. Other files in the Topical File concern the Detroit Historical Society, the Detroit Metropolitan Building Fund, the Detroit Round Table of Catholics, Jews and Protestants (responsible for the holding of an annual Brotherhood Week in Detroit), Historical Preservation, and the Sleeping Bear Dune National Lakeshore.
  - Confirmation of Edward Cardinal Mooney February 1946
    - Dispatches (from John Manning in Rome) (Box 3)
    - Newspaper Clippings
      - by John Manning (Box 3)
      - others (Box 3)
    - Miscellanea (Box 3)
  - Detroit Historical Society 1961-1967 (Box 3)
  - Detroit Metropolitan Building Fund 1961 (Box 3)
  - Detroit Round Table of Catholics, Jews and Protestants 1951-1963 (Box 3)
  - Historical Preservation Collected
    - Materials 1960-1964 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1960-1964 (Box 3)
    - Writings (Box 3)
  - Sleeping Bear Dune National Lakeshore
    - Collected Materials (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1961-1963 (Box 3)
- Writings
  Writings includes six chapters of an account of Manning's life as a newspaperman, a folder of magazine articles, a scrapbook of Manning's earliest newspaper work, mostly obituaries and small stories (ca. 1915), later clippings of Manning's editorials and columns, and a travel journal kept by Manning during a Pacific cruise (1930) and a European tour (1937). As in Correspondence, this series emphasizes the years 1960-1963, when nearly every column Manning wrote is included.
  - Autobiography: "Over-Matter", 6 chapters (Box 3)
  - Magazine Articles 1946-1961 (Box 3)
  - Newspaper Articles
    - Clippings
      - Undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Scrapbook circa 1915 (Box 4)
      - 1931-1949 (Box 4)
      - 1950-March 1961 (Box 4)
      - April-July 1961 (Box 4)
      - August-October 1961 (Box 4)
      - November 1961-March 1962 (Box 4)
      - April-October 1962 (Box 4)
      - November 1962-March 1963 (Box 4)
      - April-July 1963 (Box 4)
      - August-September, 1963 (Box 4)
      - February, 1964-1965 (Box 4)
    - Dispatches 1944-1961 (Box 4)
  - Travel Journal: 1930 (Pacific cruise) and 1937 (Europe) (Box 4)
  - Miscellanea (Box 4)
- Photographs
  The Photographs include portraits and informal photos of Manning, alone and with dignitaries and newspaper colleagues. There are also collected photographs of Greenfield Village and of the Ford Motor Company film department; and copy prints of historical photographs of views of Detroit, Michigan, ca. 1900.
  - Detroit (Box 4)
  - Greenfield Village (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4)